You may have heard
the expression
“knowledge is power.”
Well, today we’re going
to give you more power
to control your
diet and lifestyle
by giving you the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s time for the Nutrition
Facts Grab Bag
where we look at the science
on a wide variety of topics.
Today we start with
a pressing question:
why don’t health insurers
embrace plant-based eating?
Many of the diseases that
cause a constant drain
on health care budgets can be
prevented by proper nutrition.
So why aren't the big
payors getting involved?
I mean, even like a 1% decline
in excess body fat could
alone save tens of billions.
You'd think at least the health
insurance industry would try
to get people to eat healthier
to try to pay out less money.
Well, one could say the insurance
industry actually benefits from
high health care costs because
these rising costs are simply
passed on to both individuals
and employers in terms of
higher premiums, and
insurers take a fixed percentage
of these premiums
as increasing profits.
They get a piece of the pie,
so the bigger the pie —
the unhealthier everyone is —
the bigger their piece.
As such, insurers have not
done as much as they could
to help reduce health care
costs because lower costs
would hurt their bottom line.
What if there was a medication
that could successfully treat
and even reverse heart disease,
type 2 diabetes, high blood pressure,
and many other chronic conditions
without any negative side effects and
offered the promise of dramatically
reduced health care costs?
Imagine all the advertising
there would be to promote it.
Imagine how much
they would charge.
A drug that could not just
treat but cure diabetes
and these other diseases?
Then what if you were told
that medication exists today,
is available to everyone in
unlimited quantities at a low cost,
but the vast majority of the American
public has never heard about it.
You want a solution to significantly
reduce health care costs?
The solution is to use food
as medical treatment,
specifically foods made from
minimally processed plants.
One of the main barriers is simply
the current widespread belief
that once someone has
a chronic condition,
such as heart disease,
type 2 diabetes,
there's very little that can be done
to actually reverse the disease,
and the best outcome possible
is to maintain the condition
so that it just
doesn't get any worse.
The fact that a whole food
plant-based approach provides
a safe, effective, low-cost alternative
to not just eliminating symptoms
but potentially reversing
the underlying condition
without drugs or surgery
is unknown to a vast
majority of Americans.
In contrast to the pharmaceutical
industry that spends large sums
to market new drugs, there are
not big profits in promoting
a plant-based diet.
The politics surrounding healthcare
is who's going to pay for it,
instead of what kind
of healthcare is best?
And the evidence is overwhelming
that a whole food, plant-based diet
provides the best opportunity to not
only reduce the growth in spending,
but actually decrease total health
care costs more than any drug,
medical procedure, insurance reform,
or provider payment model out there.
Thankfully, the word is spreading.
A review of the evidence published
in Kaiser Permanente's journal
concluded that physicians should
consider recommending
a plant-based diet to all their
patients, especially those
with high blood pressure, diabetes,
cardiovascular disease, or obesity.
Kaiser has followed up
with user friendly guides
(freely available online)
for both physicians and patients,
explaining the benefits
and practical aspects of
implementing a plant-based diet.
So hey, why aren't all insurers
sending out such information
to all their members?
You know how all the
drug ads are like,
"Ask your doctor if this
drug is right for you."
Well, members could be
prompted to ask their physicians
about the ability of plant-based
diets to reduce or eliminate
prescription drug use,
reverse disease.
Though, of course, these
materials would also have
to list all the side effects.
Side effects include
increased energy, lower blood
pressure, improved digestion,
all while eating unlimited
quantities of satisfying food.
Ask your doctor if
plants are right for you.
Did you know that
there is little guarantee
that a dietary supplement
will actually contain
what's advertised
on the packaging?
Here’s the story.
In a video I did a few years ago,
I talked about how press releases
about the latest science coming
out of even top medical centers
were filled with
overstatements and omissions.
Medical journal press releases
suffered from similar problems,
and press releases from the
drug companies themselves
were no different, filled with
hype and exaggeration.
What about press releases
issued by the supplements industry?
Not even the companies
that published the studies,
but like trade organizations
for the multi-billion-dollar
dietary supplement industry?
Researchers found that 100% of
supplements industry press releases
contained "spin," meaning strategies
to hype or denigrate findings
to distort the results
of clinical studies.
And here's the crazy part:
industry press releases advocated
supplement use in response
to more than 90%
of even the studies that
reported no benefit or harm.
Here are the harm studies.
A study comes out showing a
supplement is actually bad for you,
and the vast majority of
independent institutions like
the National Institutes of Health
or mainstream media stories
are like "don't take it."
Duh. But the industry trade
organizations are like, "Harm?
Go for it! Buy an extra bottle."
It is, therefore, likely that the
propagation of the spin-enriched
industry press releases contributes
to the ongoing, and even burgeoning,
enthusiasm for use of supplements
in the face of accumulating evidence
of most of their ineffectiveness
and, in some cases, harm.
In some cases, people are paying
to make themselves sick.
Sadly, the science may not even
matter to many supplement users.
Most dietary supplement users said
that they would be minimally influenced
by independent, taxpayer-funded
studies contradicting
the efficacy claims of
supplement manufacturers.
Only a minority of users said they
would stop taking a supplement
if public health authorities stated
that it was just a waste of money.
The iconic image of the snake oil
salesman was actually a real dude:
Clark "the Rattlesnake King" Stanley
in 1916.
Turns out that Stanley's snake oil,
in fact, contained no snake oil at all
but rather just like spicy
mothballs and turpentine,
prosecuted under the newly enacted
Pure Food and Drug Act,
and ultimately fined a
lofty sum of $20 bucks.
And a century later, here we are
with snake oil coming out our ears,
a vast number of supplements marketed
and sold without routine oversight.
Now, the supplement industry
bristles at such talk, saying that
the supplement industry is
regulated to protect consumers.
And it's true there are definitely
laws on the books, but the ability
of regulators to successfully carry
out this mission is hampered
by the sheer number of products.
The FDA estimates there are more
than 85,000 dietary supplement
products currently available
in the U.S. alone.
So there's the sheer number,
the under reporting of adverse
side effects, the difficulty
of successfully prosecuting
cases against offenders,
and the ease with which
suppliers can rebrand products
removed from the shelves
have led to a largely
unregulated environment.
In the real world, there is little
guarantee that a supplement
will even contain what is
advertised on the packaging and
not contain unlisted ingredients,
potentially leading to significant
harms, resulting in an estimated
23,000 ER visits every year.
Now, of course, prescription drugs
don't just sicken but kill many more,
making them perhaps the
third leading cause of death,
wiping out more than
100,000 Americans, but still,
the less death and disability,
the better.
Dietary supplements
are often adulterated
with undeclared pharmaceuticals,
which could represent
an enormous risk to consumers, most
often found in erectile dysfunction,
weight loss, diabetes, and high
blood pressure supplements.
But wait a second.
What about
supplement manufacturers
who say they have independent,
third-party certification of purity?
There is a practice called
"dry labbing," a dirty little secret
of the supplements industry,
where quality assurance labs
just rubber stamp fake documents.
And if you think that's outrageous,
check out the story of BMPEA.
A researcher at Harvard published
a paper replicating prior research
from the FDA detecting a designer
amphetamine-like stimulant,
beta-methylphenylethylamine,
in various U.S. supplements
sold in the United States.
In response, one of the offenders,
Hi-Tech Pharmaceuticals,
manufacturers of weight
loss supplements like
Black Widow and Yellow Scorpion,
sued the Harvard researcher
for libel, slander, and product
disparagement, originally to the
tune of $200 million in damages.
This was all documented
in a piece by STAT,
which is an excellent source
of medical journalism
that I recommend.
The head of Hi-Tech openly
admitted that he was
"hoping that we were
able to silence this guy."
And while ultimately unsuccessful in
court, Hi-Tech's lawsuit effectively
sent a warning to other researchers.
In fact, Hi-Tech's CEO is
attributed as saying,
he "hope[s] that the long and costly
legal battle will scare away
other academics from investigating
the supplement industry."
Finally today, we
discover that those
who are eating
plant-based diets
have a reduced load of antibiotic
resistance genes in their gut.
There are nearly a million salmonella
and campylobacter infections
in children 10 and younger
each year in the United States.
Some of these infections are severe,
causing meningitis and death, and
requiring treatment with antibiotics.
The problem is that there's
an increasing problem of
antibiotic resistance among
these bugs that threatens
our ability to treat them.
Part of the problem is that the same
life-saving miracle-drug antibiotics
are being squandered
for use in food animals
for things like growth promotion
in such unhygienic,
crowded conditions,
which increases the likelihood
that pathogens like salmonella
or campylobacter will
become resistant.
But there's another problem.
The resistance determinants,
the genes that encode
antibiotic resistance,
may be transmitted from food animals
to humans through the food supply.
See, most resistant bacteria
have mobile genetic elements,
like these little circles
of DNA called plasmids,
that carry the resistance genes
that they can then pass on
to other bacteria, including
those in our own gut.
Food animals are, therefore,
a reservoir of antibiotic resistance
genes and a potential
vector for transmission
of antibiotic resistance genes to
the human intestinal microbiome.
In this study, transfer of an
antibiotic resistance plasmid
from an E. coli originating
from a chicken raised for meat
to human gut bugs was
assessed by using a model
that mimics the human intestines.
And it happened within two hours.
This spread of antibiotic resistance
genes presents an alarming scenario,
a growing concern that antibiotic
resistant bacteria present on food
can transfer their resistance genes
to the inherent gut microbiome
of the consumer.
But you don't know
until you put it to the test.
Assessing antibiotic resistance
gene loads in vegan vs. vegetarian
vs. omnivore gut bacteria.
You'd think the results
might be obvious,
but antibiotic resistance
genes are spread due to
manure application on agricultural
fields of fruits and vegetables.
Yes, massive antibiotic use in
animal farming is considered
as the greatest contributor to the
presence of antibiotic-resistant
bacteria in food of animal origin:
meats, eggs, and dairy.
Nevertheless, sewage from
treated animals may impact
on vegetables grown
on fertilized fields,
but it was largely unknown
whether, and to what extent,
antibiotic-resistant bacteria are
being transferred to vegetables
and then to the human gut until now.
Researchers looked for antibiotic-
resistant genes against sulfa drugs
like bactrim, tetracyclines,
penicillins and cephalosporins,
and streptomycin-type antibiotics
and both omnivores and vegetarians
showed a signigicantly higher
antibiotic-resistant
gene load in their guts
as compared with vegans.
There wasn't a significant difference
between omnivores and vegetarians,
but significantly lower loads in
vegans compared to omnivores,
and vegans compared to
vegetarians, the first evidence
that a vegan lifestyle
is associated with
a reduced load of human
gut antibiotic-resistant genes,
but not the last.
Fewer tetracycline resistance
genes in vegan guts and
more vancomycin resistance genes
in the guts of those who eat meat.
No surprise, since they found
a correlation between
tetracycline resistance genes
and the intake of eggs,
milk, and cheese ---
I like how there are so many
types of milk these days
they have to specify
"milk from animal sources."
And a higher incidence of
vancomycin resistance genes
was found in consumers
of eggs, poultry, fish, and seafood.
And vancomycin is one of our
antibiotics of last resort, used to
treat serious life-threatening
strep and staph infections
like MRSA (M-R-S-A).
Despite the links to dairy and
eggs, just cutting out meat
has indeed been shown to offer
an advantage in some studies,
as bacteria obtained from meat-eater
poop samples showed resistance
to a greater number of antibiotics
and carried more tested
antibiotic resistance genes compared
to the vegan or vegetarian poop.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.